I'm Campbell Bed, the chief executive
officer of of Asante Gold. We're a
mid-tier gold producer in Ghana in West
Africa.
>> Campbell, I appreciate you coming on the
show and new new to the uh platform, a
new story, and uh obviously we've never
remotely spoken before either. So
Campbell um feels like a a new new team,
new beginning. Um but it comes from a
position where perhaps the market had uh
was struggling to understand what it is
that the company was doing looking at
the share price um you know down by half
over the across across the year. Um what
do you do about it?
>> I've I've been part of the team now
since since uh March. I I came to to
Ghana in in February to have a look at
the assets. had the privilege of
spending two three weeks there on site
with the team and was very very
encouraged with what I saw. Initially I
was asked could I come as a as a
consultant and could I help with
stabilizing the asset and and moving it
forward. Um but really I I was so
entranced with the projects that's
Chirano and Bibani that uh it was a very
very easy transition for me to um to
join the company and and be part of uh
be part of this this great company's
future. Um
yes it it it's it's had a few challenges
in the past 12 months. Um the past 2
years though you've sort of always got
to be respectful of of the history of
those who came before you. They they
have picked up Asante the history of
Asante over four years old started out
as a sub 20 cent company even sort of
five six cents. Uh here it is today.
Everyone says the share price is is half
but but uh that's sort of it's it's at a
dollar today a dollar Canadian. Um but
that's a long way north of uh five or
six cents four four years ago. Um that's
been done through the hard work of uh of
our executive chairman Malik Isa the
board um the executives that have come
before me and look our six and a half
thousand employees uh contractors and
community stakeholders that are there
around the towns of Bibani and uh and
Chirano.
Last year was a challenging year for
them. Um they they did a lot of work.
They they did raise a lot of money. Um
but they have a significant number of
assets that that that we're all very
very proud of. And I guess my
opportunity is to take those assets and
sort of leverage up the work that they
did and and and sort of push them
forward. Coming in in March, there was,
you know, a few things going on. And
when people sort of say, "Yeah, what
went wrong?" I guess the guys they sort
of got out, yeah, I used, oh, you always
use that term, got out ahead of their
over their skis. Um, way too much going
on. Um, too many projects, too many sort
of things being looked at, people being
very distracted. Really hard to sort of
say, well, what did you finish? What did
you finish this week? What did you
finish this month? Um, what So, it's
been quite simple for me. we've sort of
come in and said, "Okay, look, what's
the top five things we've got to do this
week? Let's just finish those. Um, let's
do five things. Do five things, do it
well." You know, your mom and dad always
say to that to you, sort of do one
thing, do it well. Uh, you know, they
did have probably the first challenge
that tripped them up in January was they
had quite a significant um wall slip in
um in Bibby and that was quite a major
major event. It really did set the
company back. Uh but at the same time,
our other asset, Chirano, which is 15
kilometers away, wonderful underground
and open pit operation, has continued
on, just continues on. It just continues
to perform. The team there um just a a
wonderful team of underground operators
and open pit operators. We've got five
underground mines there. We have about
four or five open pits. Um and a mill
does about sort of 3 3 1/2 million tons
peranom as well. That's just continued
on continued to chunk away 10,000 11,000
ounces every single month. That's
allowed the team at Bibani to focus on,
you know, okay, we've got to get in and
we've got to sort of work through this
this this stripping exercise. And that
stripping exercise is still ongoing. um
it'll be ongoing through to the end of
the year but you know happy to report
they are making really really great
progress. The other challenge at Bibani
has been the sort of metallurgical
characteristics of of the ore that's
coming in
um quite a high sulfide sulfidic ore u
and they've been transitioning the the
plant to about a 50% sort of flotation
process. uh they built and commissioned
the sulfide recovery plant last year and
one of the first things that we did was
sort of yeah was thankfully it was only
a couple of tweaks but we've sort of got
that up and that that running earlier
this year that's been that's running
well and now we're sort of tying that
into the plant and there's about four or
five other projects that need to be tied
into that plant to get that plant
operating. It's even today it's probably
about
2 months 2 months away from sort of
really starting to get it to the to
where we want it to be. Um and I guess
one of the things I've often sort of
said in the past couple of months to
everyone is let's finish the key
projects that sort of um some of the
some of the sort of sulfide recovery,
some gravity circuit work, uh carbon
regeneration kils. Um, we got to get a
pebble crusher in and and these and an
extra flotation cap tank capacity. Get
those projects in, get them working, and
then let's sweat the asset. Um, one of
the things the the previous management
were doing was they would be doing that,
but they're halfway done. Right, let's
start another five or six projects.
Let's probably start another 10
projects. And we're saying, no, no,
stop. Let's just invest in what we've
got. Let's finish those and then let's
let's make the plant run. Let's let's
sweat the asset. Repeating myself. And
and get it to start generating cash. Um
we're starting to have some stability in
the mining now over the next month or
two. It's really about stability in the
plant and then you know really sort of
working towards as we sort of said in
this outlook recently working towards
the second half quarter fall really sort
of rolling into that rolling towards the
end of the year and setting ourselves up
for a great 2027.
>> Okay. So you you've hit upon um a lot of
different topics there and and a lot of
areas of the business that you're
looking at. Can I can I just sort of
dive in if you don't mind to um the
ultimate goal here which is obviously if
you're looking at an ASIC which is you
know at or above market consensus for
gold price at the moment it you know it
doesn't bode well for for margin. So
when you talk about stabilization, cost
control, capital discipline,
accountability, focus, all of these
fantastic words. Can you can you just
convert that into precisely what you
mean? like we're not going to go after
chasing lots of different projects, you
know, um or activities. Um and we're
going to focus on um Bibani and
obviously Chirano. What exactly does
that mean and why is that going to drive
the cost down? Um, two key drivers of of
a high all in sustaining cost aisk.
Um, over the past 6 months has been that
high level of stripping. Um, and I would
say an excess level of stripping. We
we've literally had to double down on
the on the stripping. Uh, so so and
look, that is that is going to be
ongoing. That's that's a sort of a a
part and parcel of this wonderful large
pit of of Bibani. Uh that will be
continuing on. But as we get down into
the bottom of back back down into the
bottom of Bibani um main pit, that's
where we start to see the grade lift. Um
sort of moving that grade from about you
know over the past six months or so it's
been 1.3 1.4 grams per ton head grade
thereabouts. Um we should start to see
that heading towards sort of 1.7 1.8 8 g
per ton towards the end of 2020 26 and
then stay there and sort of keep keep
sort of chunking along in in in 2027.
Grade is one of the great contributors
to reducing your cost. It increases your
ounces your ounce profile. Um but also
the the other contributor to the oil and
sustaining cost has been this
significant project expenditure on a
number of these projects. bringing those
projects to an end and just focusing on
operating the asset and operating that
asset well and then starting to look for
opportunities to reduce the operating
cost of that asset. When you're in that
build phase, you're just trying to run
it. Something breaks, get it in.
Something breaks, get it in. Just run
run. And and and and an operating team
really tends to lose focus. Um, you
know, a great way of thinking about
running a mine or running any sort of
factory, any sort of operation is it's a
hamster wheel. It just every Monday you
do what you do on a Monday. Every
Tuesday you do what you do on a Tuesday.
Wednesday reporting. Thursday starting
to think about the next week. Friday,
what's the forecast for next week? What
are the things we've got to be thinking
about this week that we make sure that
next week is a success? But if you're
trying to build things, that takes you
away from that cadence. It takes you
away from that discipline um of watching
your operating costs, watching your
throughput, watching your gold
production. It's it's it's it's and I
guess that's why I've been talking about
stabilization, talking about finishing
projects, is trying to get that
operation into that cadence of of
steadystate operation. We're still quite
a ways away from that at Bibani. As I
sort of saying, there's still a month or
two of work to do and and we're sort of
slowly getting down into the main pit
and getting getting that working. Um, so
there's still a bit to go, but that is
the objective. So when you sort of say
what does stabilization mean? It's
getting there to that steady cadence of
steady state operations.
>> Okay. So that that mindset is being
implemented. Um, and I'm just wonder I'm
just wondering how you help the the look
there it's a new new new board new
senior management team have have come in
here you're looking at it differently
through different uh lenses I get it but
how much is in your control and how much
is it simply spreading costs across more
ounces because you know I'm wondering
where the big chunks of change are going
to come from like do do you say to the
management team look we need the first
500,000 ounce of cost reduction to come
from the following and then we'll worry
about the next thing or is it just lots
of small changes will make a difference
eventually?
>> It is to a certain extent. Um so from a
management new management point of view
as said the new CEO um I've I've been in
the in the role now as the CEO for since
April and um took over from Dave Anthony
who retired done a wonderful job for for
four years to to get the company from
where it was four years ago to to where
it is today. Um, and then I've been
really privileged recently to have um,
Mr. Glenn Baldwin join me uh, in Ghana.
Um, Glenn also a mining engineer and
probably I didn't speak about my
background. I'm a mining engineer. U,
I'm a mining engineer from Perth,
Western Australia. Over 35 years of
experience. Um, started my career in
Kamba in the in the gold fields of of
Western Australia. Spent five or six
years working there. And then I've had
the privilege, the wonderful privilege
and and mining, mining gives you this
wonderful privilege of working all over
the world. There isn't a continent I
haven't worked on. Um, Asia, North
America, South America, Europe, uh, and
and Africa. Uh, I' I've I've been been
privileged to to do it all. Um, my main
focus is is underground, but I've also
got a deep deeper level of exposure and
experience with with open pits. Uh and
Glenn brings that similar lens and and
experience level. Glenn's from um
Australia as well. Um started his career
in in in South Australia um Mount Eiza,
a lot of work up there and uh then also
has spent the past decade or two
overseas and he's actually moved
full-time to um to Ghana. He's sort of
situated there as as the chief
development officer. So it's it's
between the pair of us. Um, we're sort
of I guess we have that privilege of
experience. We we bring that privilege
of experience. We bring that privilege
of time and and and
that's one of the things I really really
enjoy is is taking that experience to
teams, new teams in particular, and just
sort of saying, "Guys, okay, here's the
playbook.
Number one objective is get to a
cadence, steady state cadence. Once
you're in that steadyst state cadence,
it it is Matthew, it is in all honesty,
it's little incremental wins. There's
very very few, you know, big bangs that
you go, aha, $500,
$500 per ounce, bang, it's gone. You
know, just doesn't happen. Um we did
talk about we've talked about in a
couple of public announcements that
we've we've either sort of cancelled,
deferred or pushed out um large amounts
of capital. Um and that's sort of $50
million worth of of capital. Um sort of
say 50 million at least. Um and one
thing bring me back to I want to talk
about the wrap project as well which has
been quite a high spend will be going
forward but how it's a wonderful project
that sort of sits outside the mining
that we're doing. Um, but yeah, just
focusing on that 50 million, we've we've
been able to, Glenn and I look at a
number of the projects that the team was
doing and say, do we need them today?
Can we push them out? Are they be doing
are being done well using our
experience? We we've asked a number of
sort of external supporters to have a
look at things for us and they've come
back and said, well, maybe you sort of
want to just modify what you're doing
here. Why don't we just pause and have a
look? Um, so you know, a couple of the
things we've just paused them for now.
Not saying that we won't come back to
them in 2027, but we'll come back to
them with sort of better capital
discipline, better design, and and and
bitter work. Back to operating costs.
Um, you know, I I sort of, you know,
we've been affected, as everyone has, by
that diesel price. We've we've seen a
significant increase in in the diesel
price over the past couple of um months,
um, courtesy of we know what. Um labor
uh labor costs always doesn't matter
where you are in the world one of your
largest largest costs and um and then
you know your supply chain that's always
a unique opportunity. We are working
hard on our supply chain both in making
it efficient um and but also in sort of
you know retendering looking at things
asking asking our suppliers um you know
can you help us here and I do have to
give a big shout out to all of our
suppliers in Gata um and and our
stakeholders and our contractors they've
been incredibly supportive over the over
the past two years uh I won't name names
and stuff but but there are a number of
companies out there who have been very
very supportive of the company through
thick and thin and I guess we're really
really privileged there that a couple of
times in the past couple of months we've
gone to them and said hey look can you
help us out here um and they've gone
yeah yeah okay no problem um so that's
been we've been able to sort of but
we've been able to demonstrate to them
um that you know through us bringing
that stability they can see a longer
life as well. Um, one of the things that
we we recently talked we put out was our
new reserve. Um, and and that's sort of
showing that there's over a 7-year mine
life at both at both um, Chirano and and
at Bibbyani. Um, you know, using just
indicated material and then we we sort
of always talk about our inferred
resource base and then sort of the
future. uh and and and and that that
sort of is starting to give people sort
of confidence that this is this is not
just a three-year operation or a
two-year operation. It's a minimum of
sevenyear operation and then, you know,
out out and beyond. I'm not really sure
how how public I can be about sort of
saying how long those sort of things
are, but but I'm very very confident
that this is a very very long life
asset. Both of them, Cherano and Bibani,
the expiration upside is extraordinary.
Um but by bringing it back to that sort
of operating cost, cost discipline,
cadence, that's how we'll make it in the
short term a success and
yeah be here for for a lot longer as a
as a result of that stability and that
success.
>> Okay. Okay. Well, let me let me can
bring you back to this kind of deferred
or cancelled 50 million of capital and
that sort of attitude to um being a sort
of a a good um I guess allocator of
capital 32 3600 ASIC you know you need
that sustainable ASIC to be lower when
you look around look I'm not asking it
for any kind of formal guidance just
saying when you look around Ghana which
has got a lot of gold outfits there in
fact that whole western Sahill has when
you look at comparable projects effects.
Do you think this is going to be a
$3,000 mine, a $25 thousand mine, a
$2,000 mine? Where what do you think's
potentially? What What do you think the
potential is if you get it right?
>> It's it's below 3 thou long long term it
will be. Well, it'll be below $3,000 an
ounce. Yes. Yes. That's that's that's um
that is that is our objective. um you
know that's that's where we're we're
we're aiming for and and I'm pretty
certain that you know through 2027 we'll
we'll be able to demonstrate to our
investors that sort of that's the
trajectory that we're on. Um is it below
$2,000 an ounce? No. I I don't think
anyone can can look you in the eye,
Matthew, right now and tell you that
below $2,000 an ounce is is a serious
number. Um it's been quite extraordinary
how we've seen that cost inflation
across the globe uh in the mining
industry since straight off from muzz
all of that sort of stuff diesel labor
supply chain logistics um just all of
those things has lifted lifted
everybody's cost base and it's not just
gold in West Africa it's gold in
Australia it's iron ore it's lithium you
name it we're all seeing that cost
inflation so everyone needs to be
realistic about those sort of things um
but back to us uh our yes I that's 2027
that's our objective to sort of show
everyone the trajectory is is down there
but we'll only do it through cadence and
discipline and and focus um and just
sort of getting getting our assets to
work and demonstrating to everybody that
our assets are going to deliver like we
say we're say that they can just talking
about the kind of financing structure
that you've kind of got in place you've
kind of got a like I think it's 150
million senior facility and up to 125
subordinated and you've got a 50 million
gold stream. Um, what what's that for?
>> Well, all of that material, all of those
those facilities were to build the
plant, to build the mine, to to to to
start a gold company. Um, yeah. Look,
you know, it's uh
you
it doesn't get built for free.
>> No, no,
>> it it Yeah,
>> but what's a building I guess a cheeky
way of saying that what are you what are
you what's the kind of the ATM? what's
the kind of a cash machine that you're
building with that you know and then you
know how do you how do you manage that
or you know um bring that down
>> you build a house you borrow money and
then you work to pay it off I can't be
clearer than that right um and and this
this this asset once it gets up
operating uh I mean previous previous
guidance had been sort of you know 400
500,000 ounces perom um that's we
withdrew that last year and that's
that's not something we're planning to
reinstate at all. Um, you know, people
just shouldn't be thinking about those
sort of things. Um, again,
we're just sort of focusing on what's in
front of us right now. Getting
continuing to operate Chirano. Chirano
is a is a massive opportunity. I I I
just see it as an enormous enormous
growth opportunity for for the company
and for the country really. Um it it's
it's it's five underground mines.
Enormous exploration potential for those
at depth. We sort of set out the
opportunities there in our in our sort
of out in our exploration and reserve
update. People can sort of see the the
expiration that we're sort of predicting
and thinking about in in the Chirano
undergrounds. We've also started to sort
of talk about you've got the two shears,
the Chirano shear and the Bibani shear
that run up over sort of 80 kilometers
of of of strike. There's enormous hardly
been explored. The company has been over
the past four years solely focused on
the Toronto mines and the Bibani mines.
Well, what's to the north and south
along those things? and we're just sort
of starting to encourage our exploration
teams to get out there and start looking
at uh you know a long strike uh and and
they've been doing that and you know the
the Abuabo pit that we've been mining
for the past four or five months is a
perfect example of that up at up at
Chirano was like guys we challenge you
find find some sort of we just need an
extra 20 30,000 tons a month to be
coming into the Chirano mill there's
that sort of capacity what do you got
Well, you know, here's something we
prepared earlier and um it it's it's uh
you know, it's been sort of feeding into
the mill. It's finished at the moment,
but but it gave gave the um the the
plant about six six nine months of good
production. Um and we've we've sort of
stopped because we've taken the top off.
We've got the oxide material and they've
you've now sort of got a uh getting into
sort of the sulfide sulfidic material.
Now, that material doesn't really go
through the Cherano plant. Um and one of
the tasks for us in 2027 and it's one of
the projects we've deferred in the short
run is to create a a hall road between
Bibani and Chirano and bringing that
hall road between the two company two
two companies two projects um starts to
create enormous synergies whether it be
on the supply side so you know we've
we've got literally got two independent
stores. They're 20 km apart and so in
many respects there's duplication um of
the stores. So you start being able to
bring stores together. We start being
able to bring people and technical
services together, financial services
together, human resources services
together, all sorts of opportunities to
sort of bring people together all under
the one roof roof um and and sort of
services and you know start to share
knowledge and all of that. But also
sulfide ore comes over to Bibani which
has been constructed as a sulfide plant.
Oxide material goes over to Chirano
which has been constructed as an oxide
plant. And and so and and hard rock hard
rock non-sulfide plant which is what our
undergrounds are. Wish our undergrounds
were oxide go through a whole lot
faster. Um but um but yeah, so that's
that's the sort of strategy that's
starting to sort of that that we're sort
of starting to tease out of the business
and will be teasing out of the business
sort of through 2027. And I guess the
evolution that you're going to see
through 27 26 27 into 28 um is is all of
that sort of stuff starting to come
together. How do you deal with with with
with all of those facilities and
everything? Well, that's all modeled in
with, you know, as this place becomes
more successful dealing with all of
those facilities, dealing with that
debt. It's very, very simple to start
dealing with it into 2027 and 2028. So,
so that's our plan. We know it's there.
Um, it was taken on for a purpose. It's
been used. We've got two great assets.
Um and you know you will will be dealing
and we'll we'll start to execute on
those assets start to sort of have them
start to sweat and generate cash and
from that as well as expiration and all
the other things of growing growing
production we will be starting to put
that we we will deal with the
liabilities that we have and and that's
that's all going to be taken care of
through production. Look, I know I
appreciate you and the new management
team are really quite neat. You know,
you're three, four months in. Um,
>> y
>> and it's been a balance sheet repair
exercise that you've been you've been
looking at um rather than growth. But
some of the things you just talked about
are grow growth components albeit um
facilitating growth into growth uh at at
some point. So where do you think the
market where in fact where do you think
your existing shareholders are perhaps
looking at this and going okay we're
going to give you some time to get get
your feet under the table and execute
come up with a plan and then start
executing that plan. What do you think
they value most and maybe why are they
wrong or why are they right because you
talked about exploration we got Bibani
underground. We got Shani plant
improvements. You could you could pay
down debt. You could you there's lots of
things that you've just said that you
could do with it. But in terms of the
weight that you put on each of those
things, what's important to you and what
you think they think existing
shareholders think is the most important
important way to allocate their capital.
>> The majority of shareholders that I've
been speaking to and it's sort of one of
the first things you you do. You sort of
get on the phone and start talking to
your larger shareholders. You're always
happy to speak to to all shareholders.
Every shareholder has a right to
understand what's going on. Um we we
we've been less than communicative over
the past couple of months because of
sort of like oh I don't know give me a
bit of time to get my feet under the
desk and and have a look and still
sometimes every day we we learn
something new. The majority of them say
the potential of this place is enormous.
We just want to see you unlock this
potential. Um the cheapest ounces are
your own ounces. you know, no one no
one, you know, no one no one wants
Asante to go and do M&A in 2026.
Everyone, all the shareholders want us
to be focusing on our reserve base,
unlocking that and then focusing on the
f the horizon and the future, which is
our exploration potential and starting
to unlock that. Um because
everybody's sort of look has looked at
it and gone there is a massive
opportunity here. Guys, put your time
and effort and energy into unlocking
that. That's that's what our
shareholders want to see from us. And um
it's pretty straightforward. It's the
Cherado shear and it's the Viviani
shear. It's sort of these wonderful two
little structures that sort of run over
80 kilometers through our land. And um
that's that's sort of what we're um
going to be sort of focusing on. Thank
you very much. Um that's what we're
going to be focusing on for the next
couple of years. It's dinner time here.
>> Okay. Well, in which I will let you go.
It's just appreciate that. And obviously
23 24 million bucks of expiration um
helps um get get after those new answers
as you say which could have a material
effect on on um cost margins and etc.
So, look, Camel, I appreciate you coming
on um and chatting to us um this evening
because I know it's late there um for
for sure. Um stay in touch. Let us know
how you get on. I'd love these kind of I
don't know if you're going to call us a
turnaround story or stabilization story
or or Asante 2.0, whatever you whatever
you call it, do stay in touch. Okay.
>> Yeah. No, Matthew. Anytime. Yeah. We
look forward to keeping um keeping in
touch and keeping everyone else informed
as well. Thank you very much for having
me.